Finding Aid for Letters, Documents, & Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Letters, Documents, and Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
  - 1915 June 29. H[enry] C[abot] Lodge TLS to Charles G. Washburn; Nahant, Massachusetts, 3 pages; A great deal of political content, primarily concerning party politics. There are brief comments on women's suffrage, national prohibition, and "social welfare legislation;" however, the bulk of the letter stresses the importance of getting Wilson out of office. "National prohibition and woman suffrage are not party questions and divide the progressives as they do the Republicans." References Theodore [Roosevelt] and [John W.?] Weeks. Written on U.S. Senate, Committee on Private Land Claims stationery.
  - 1916 May 11. John D[avison] Rockefeller, Jr. TLS to Albert J. Weil; New York [City, New York], 1 page; Encourages Weil to establish himself in a single church during his New York visits. "Otherwise one is so apt to drift from church, or attend none, and thereby lose the opportunities for Christian service and the helpful and restraining influence which affiliation with some one church affords."
  - 1916 May 27. J[ames] W. Wadsworth, Jr. TLS to Reverend Paul R. Hickock; Washington, D.C., 2 pages; Wadsworth reflects on fraternity life at Yale, and its distinctions from fraternities at other colleges. Acknowledges the great value that fraternities have with young men and for America. Includes manuscript revisions. Written on U.S. Senate letterhead.
  - 1916 June 29. Charles W. Eliot TLS to Perriton Maxwell; Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1 page; Comments on American men serving in the armed forces, noting that the "immense majority" of American mothers are in no need of a message on "the subject of giving their sons to the Country." "...it is the duty of every American, in time of war, to forego the privileges, which as a free man he exercises in time of peace, and to surrender to the State his right 'to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness'. " Believes American preparation would benefit from copying "the legislation of the ancient Swiss Republic."
  - 1916 July 12. And[rew] D[ickson] White TLS to Reverend Paul R. Hickock; Ithaca, New York, 5 pages; Typed letter with manuscript revisions. White reflects on fraternities at Cornell University. He acknowledges the "evils" of fraternities, but emphasizes their potential for positive effects and recent improvements. A fellow fraternity member, Theodore Munger, "always came out with hearty expressions of joy that he had lived to see so much of the old follies, fooleries, and boyish pranks done away with." Considering organizing the Cornell student body "into clubs on the general plan of the fraternities."
  - 1916 July 19. John Malone ALS to Margaret; McAllen, Texas, 2 pages; Letter from Malone, of the 12th U.S. National Guard, Company F. Describes trying environmental conditions and how soldiers killed four Mexicans "for cutting up one of our boys." Notes how they left the bodies to serve as an "example of the rest." Uses racial slurs. Has given up beer. Written on W.C.T.U. and Methodist Church Soldiers' Reading Room stationery. See also John Malone ALS to Margaret; 1917 February 15.
  - 1916 September 28. Richard C[ockburn] Maclaurin TLS to W[illiam] B. Munro; [Cambridge, Massachusetts], 1 page; Congratulations on the success of Munro's cooperative branch store. Pleased to hear of "the good service that Major Cole has rendered." On official MIT "Office of the President" stationery. Sent to Professor W. B. Munro, Harvard Cooperative Society.
  - 1916 October 7. Charles W. Eliot TLS to W. R. Castle, Jr.; Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1 page; Will sign copies of his book, The Road towards Peace. Comments on recent labor legislation. "[B]oth parties truckle to the labor organizations incessantly." Notes the strength of the "Canadian law for the investigation of industrial disputes" in preventing strikes. Most Americans sympathize with strikers, because they feel strikes will raise wages. Recent events may alter this opinion, as "they are beginning to suffer from the increased cost of transportation, food, clothing, and houses,-- an increased cost which is caused chiefly by higher wages."
  - 1916 October 30. Charles W. Eliot TLS to Perriton Maxwell; Cambridge, Massachusetts, 3 pages [total]; "I enclose a brief statement about the teachings of the great War in respect to Christianity." Includes a signed, two-page piece about the teachings of Jesus and how organized religion corrupted them. Calls for a return Christianity's "simple essentials," abandoning "rites, dogmas, and creeds" which failed to restrain man's baser instincts. Hopes for greater respect for the heroism "of the doctor, nurse, fireman, policeman, rescuer, and lonely struggler against want, sickness, and temptation," rather than just reverence for soldiers.
  - 1917 February 15. John Malone ALS to Margaret; McAllen, Texas, 2 pages; Letter from Malone, of the 12th U.S. National Guard, Company F. Hopes that his last letter did not hurt her feelings. Racial hatred. "Well Margaret we had a narrow escape the other night a few greaser's started something and we finished it we just shot his place so full of holes that it looked like a rifle range we were going to see how close we could come to his eyebrows with our six shooter's only the officer's had to but in he's lucky he's liven we just love to shoot these greaser's down here for pastime or to amuse our self's." Written on "The Army and Navy Young Men's Christian Association" stationery. See also John Malone ALS to Margaret; 1916 July 19. (Box 10)
  - 1917 March 15. Joseph B. Tordoff ALS to "Friend"; Camp Kearny, California, 5 pages; Headquarters Company, 143rd Field Artillery. Serving as the "radio man of the second Battalion," describes the equipment he uses and having to know how to fix telephones in the trenches. Notes weather at camp and troubles with mud. Comments on the price of provisions in San Diego. Describes a recent review, which included his regiment, the Utah Field Artillery, and the "144th (Grizzles?) crack regiment." The 144th has to borrow guns, horses, and signal kits. Written on illustrated YMCA stationery, "National War Work Council Army and Navy," with images of the YMCA logo and American flag.
  - 1917 September 10. Charlie ALS to Myrtle; France, 8 pages; Apologizes for length between letters; mentions censors. Comments on British Expeditionary Forces, the locations where they are serving, the food issued to them, and cooking in the trenches. Brief mention of the Battle of the Somme and his rations during it. Describes trench warfare, "when the opposing sides sit down & face one another ‘to gain time' shelling, bombing & shooting one another more or less frequently." Notes lulls in the fighting; time spent at camps and in French villages. Comments on clothing and mud in the trenches, and soldiers' willingness to risk leaving the trenches to dry their feet. "Even in the Battle of Arras in late spring, I have seen men literally stuck fast in the mud." Describes fighting in the beginning of the war, with reliance on field guns, and the shift to trench warfare. Strategies of fighting evolved due to trenches and attempts to force combatants "to get a move on," as in the battle of Neuve Chapelle. Notes the advantages of defense rather than offense, with "Barbed wire entanglements scores of feet thick, the fire of machine guns as numerous as daisies in a June..." Mentions the use of "gas & liquid fire," his serving for 27 months, and receiving the Meritorious Service Medal.
  - [1918] January 5. Edwin ALS to Folks; Camp McClellan, Anniston, Alabama, 2 pages; Comments on a recent snowstorm and the heaters in the camp. Describes being quarantined and coming down with measles. "Send a cake down because we only get what sick people get." Written on Y.M.C.A. "With the Colors" letterhead, with images of Y.M.C.A. logo and American flag. See also: Edwin ALS to his uncle; September 3, 1918.
  - 1918 February 15. Franklin D[elano] Roosevelt TLS to J. C. Heddle; Washington D.C., 1 page; Thanks Heddle for answering the Navy's call for binoculars. "The glasses will be very useful in the prosecution of Naval Operations until victory is won." Will return the binoculars at the end of the war if possible. Written on Navy Department, Assistant Secretary's Office letterhead. Accompanied by: 1. Check for $1.00 from the Navy Disbursing Office to J. C. Heddle 2. Typed letter (copy) explaining the purpose of the check. "Navy's Call for Binoculars, Spy-Glasses, Telescopes, Sextants and Chronometers."
  - 1918 March 22. [Barbé?] TLS to Mac; Lonoke, Arkansas, 1 page; Comments on Mac's transfer to the Cavalry. "I suppose politics plays a great big part in the Intelligence Dept., more so than in other branches of t[h]e service." Notes other men in the service, poking fun at one's interest in life insurance. Describes a married couple living in his house, "He is a Phi Kap from Columbia and is a flier." Mentions flying commencing in Lonoke soon and the arrival of cadets. Comments on another Phi Kap who married an actress "and she sure startles the natives here with her rags." "Everybody back here thinks the war is going to last for at least a couple of years longer.... I think myself it will go a year or two, but am hoping it will end before then. I would like to get out to-morrow if I could."
  - 1918 May 6. Neilson Poe ALS to Jane Righter; France, 4 pages; Poe, of the 28th Infantry, AEF. Poe's close friend Pardee is engaged to a woman that he once courted and feels betrayed. Currently in rest billets. Future orders unknown. Frequent practice alerts make it impossible to tell whether alarms are fake or real "you don't know... whether you are coming back after a short hike or are really going up to one of the advance positions. You have to pack all your belongings & you have a very few minutes to do it in." Recently participated in artillery and infantry assault on the front lines. Aerial dogfights.
  - [1918] May 31. Malbone ALS to Gladys; Paris, [France], 2 pages; Malbone, a Red Cross worker, writes from the Gare du Nord the day after the Germans took Soissons. Vivid description of the influx of refugees from the Aisne valley. Eloquent and thoughtful reflection on the refugees, war, democracy, liberty, and equality. Discusses strong women from the country, children, war and the French people, and feeding the thousands of refugees. Remarks on the French and American spirit and the ties that bind them. Distinguishes between a militaristic German government and the mass of German people. On American Red Cross (Croix-Rouge Américaine) stationery.
  - 1918 July 8. Tho[ma]s F. Campbell ALS to I. F. Campbell; [France], 4 pages; Sgt. Thomas F. Campbell, Co. B, 306th Infantry, 77th Division. Writes from a hospital. "if luck wasn't with me, we would be prisoners of the 'hun' and that is pretty bad..." He and four other men injured in a ten-minute fight. Hand grenade shrapnel removed from his feet (12-14 pieces). American nurses are patient and pretty.
  - 1918 July 14. "Cecil" ALS to "Grandma"; Camp Macarthur, Texas, 4 pages; 123rd Ordnance Depot. Promoted to corporal after eight days; currently serves as the "private secretary to the commanding officer," and expects to be promoted to an ordnance sergeant. Notes pay and his desire to be stationed in California. Friends and family sending him fruits and other food. Comments on food in the camp and his awareness that the variety will change once he goes overseas. See also, "Cecil" ALS to "Grandma," November 20, 1918.
  - 1918 August 12. H. A. Dickson ALS to Geo[rge] W[ylie] P[aul] Hunt; s.l., 1 page; Company A, 314th Engineers, American Expeditionary Forces. Written on a postcard with a printed American Eagle atop a shield, with the stars and stripes. "Well Governor, things are happening near and about here." Mentions the "great drive" and hopes that fighting will cease before winter. Looking forward to receiving letters to lessen his lonesomeness. Includes censor stamp.
  - 1918 August 14. W[illiam] H. Cowles ALS to Colonel C. W. Cowles; s.l., 4 pages; H. is getting along very well; his nurse moved nearby. Gives news from the front lines. "I am glad I came over altho' at times it is dull, dirty, and dangerous and I would not miss it for a fortune." Allied plane shot down a German bomber. "Blew up hitting the ground but from the looks of it, it was a monster."
  - 1918 August 15. A. L. Kemp ALS to R. B. Eastman; Aix-les-Bains, France, 1 page; Picture postcard with image of Hôtel Bernascon, Aix-les-Bains. Spending his seven days of leave at Aix-les-Bains, "a wonderful summer Resort." Includes censor stamp.
  - 1918 August 24. H. L. Rogers Typed circular; s.l., 5 pages; "American Expeditionary Forces Headquarters Services of Supply Office of the Chief Quartermaster, A.E.F." H. L. Rogers, Major General, U.S. Army Chief Quartermaster. Publishing information received by the supply office about which items can be distributed, which have been discontinued or will not be issued, and particulars about various items in use. Notes on rolling kitchens and cooking equipment, marmites and milk cans, dishes. Details on bunks, gear, furniture, tools, flags and standards. Specifics on repairing office machinery. Rules about coffins and grave markers.
  - 1918 August 31. "Curly" ALS to "Moore"; s.l., 3 pages; Company K, 2nd Pioneer Infantry, American Expeditionary Force. Comments on the cigarettes Moore sent and mishaps with mail. Was quickly sent overseas after arriving at camp. "I imagine the Army life is quite different from the days when you were in a uniform. Over here it is like one big family." Comments on Commissioned Officers fraternizing with other soldiers. Inquires after events at the Texaco station and whether anyone else has been drafted yet. See also, "Curly" TLS to "Moore," November 17, 1918.
  - [19]18 September 3. Edwin ALS to Uncle Simon; Camp Wadsworth, Spartanburg, South Carolina, 4 pages; Medical Replacement Unit #25. Compliments his uncle on the supportive letter he sent. "The knowledge that those at home are behind us, striving for the end of this catastrophe makes for the one thing we all need and that is gritty nerve & stamina." Comments on his turning to religion in the Army. Notes adjusting to army food, receiving inoculations and vaccines. "As the Medical Corp is consider the paramount branch of the service and its non-commissioned officers ranking higher than those in any other branch of Uncle Sam's army I am intending to make a hard upward fight for position." Written on Y.M.C.A. "With the Colors" letterhead, with images of Y.M.C.A. logo and American flag. See also: Edwin ALS to his Folks; January 5, [1918].
  - [19]18 September 13. AL to Mother; Camp Mills, Long Island, New York, 1 page; "I am over at the Y.M.C.A. but I'm not supposed to be, I sneaked out as I had nothing to do." Comments on his clothing, noting of his hobnail shoes, "I can't hardly carry them, they are so heavy." Written on Y.M.C.A. "With the Colors" letterhead, with images of Y.M.C.A. logo and American flag.
  - 1918 October 10. Wenzel [Kryzanosky] ALS to Irma Kryzanosky; s.l., 3 pages; Lieutenant, Motor Supply Train 415, Motor Truck Company 455, American Expeditionary Forces. Disappointed in the mail for not delivering her letters. "What are the news and how is the war, what about peace?" Making progress in his sector, "takeing prisoners every day." Hopes the war ends soon, so they can be reunited. Wishes they had stayed in Puerto Rico. Envelope includes censor stamp, "officers mail."
  - 1918 October 12. "Kenneth" ALS to Mr. Gibbs; [near Bordeaux, France], 5 pages; Notes restrictions placed on his communications (on account of censors). Was stationed near Bordeaux, France, living in a "large chateau." Describes the country around Bordeaux, his attempts to learn French, and speaking with locals. Was selected to attend school and has been working with rifles and grenades. Believes he will be restless when he returns home, on account of moving about so frequently. A long line of soldiers waited at the Quartermaster store because they had chocolate in stock. Enclosing the chocolate wrapper and seal [not included]. Mentions the "sugar question" and wonders how they are handling it back home. Cannot provide more details on the events at the front than can be otherwise obtained. "The President handled the Kaiser in his usual crafty way and we are anxiously awaiting the answer. Of course we all know what the final answer will be...." Written on Y.M.C.A. "On Active Service" stationery.
  - 1918 November 6. Paul ALS to Mother; [London, England], 12 pages; Describes his travel to Liverpool on board the S.S. Megantic, White Star Line, including other passengers and evasive maneuvers. Travelled to London by train. Describes London and darkening the city at night. Notes air raid shelters, food rations, and beliefs that the war is almost over. Ordered to Queenstown, Ireland. Written on American Officers' Club stationery. See also Paul ALS to Mother, November 12, 1918; November 23, 1918.
  - [19]18 November 12. Paul ALS to Mother; Queenstown, Ireland, 12 pages; Signing of the armistice has altered his plans and made future movements uncertain. "Of course all flying (except joy hops) has been suspended." Describes his travels from London to Queenstown. American naval men forbidden to visit Cork, "on account of dangerous complications with the Sinn Feiners." Describes the Irish countryside and his station. See also Paul ALS to Mother, November 6, 1918; November 23, 1918.
  - 1918 November 13. "Tad" ALS to "Peggy"; s.l., 8 pages; Battery B, 56th Artillery Regiment, Coast Artillery Corps, American Expeditionary Forces. Comments on the end of the war. "I just guess the huns know who is boss now... When I first heard it—well I cannot explain just how I did feel." A portion of the letter was cut out by a censor. Describes barrages, including by an African American artillery outfit. Notes military police with German prisoners of war. Describes the shelling of a village and the American movement up the main road. Germans with stretchers helped the Red Cross without guards. "... ever since early morning details of germans have been carrying in our wounded just as if they had always been with us and they sure have saved some lads." Appreciates receiving letters from home. Written on Y.M.C.A. stationery.
  - 1918 November 16. Joseph C. Holbrook ALS to Effie Granade; France, 8 pages; Battery Co. 11. Signed "JC," with purple stamped signature "Joseph C. Holbrook 1st. Lieut. Q. M. C., U. S. A. Detailed description of the armistice celebration in "a large city" in France on November 11. Cheers, songs, music by an African American U.S. band, also a white U.S. band," including the Star Spangled Banner, Limey Stable Blues, etc. Streetlights lit for the first time in four years. Children shouting "La Guerre est fini; mon père sera à sa maison beintôt," women dressed in mourning: "To me, that is the most pathetic sight I've ever witnessed. They looked on with an expression of mixed joy and sorrow." French and American soldiers danced. City covered with allied flags: "To be in a foreign land, war-torn, bleeding but triumphant, and to see 'The Stars and Bars' waving in majesty and triumph from every door is Heaven on earth and makes a fellow happy that he is an American and willing to be a Champion of right." Nurses will be giving a "Victory Dance" to the officers.
  - 1918 November 17. "Curly" TLS to "Moore"; s.l., 1 page; Corporal Alfred Vos, Headquarters Detachment, Army Service Corps, American Expeditionary Forces. Disappointed that Moore is the only one "of the Texaco bunch" that has written. "I guess the rest of them are so busy making money on their jobs for the government that they haven't time to write a guy that is over here on this side of the water." Brief mention of celebration on account the signing of the armistice. Has been transferred to Army Headquarters. See also, "Curly" ALS to "Moore," August 31, 1918.
  - 1918 Novembr 20. "Cecil" TLS to "Grandma"; [Camp Macarthur, Texas], 2 pages; Remarks on the end of the war and his uncertainty about when he will be sent home. Sent pictures of himself to family members. Family news, including the poisoning of a pet. Notes rains and flooding of local rivers. Written on Y.M.C.A. stationery. See also, "Cecil" ALS to "Grandma," July 14, 1918.
  - 1918 November 23. Paul ALS to Mother; Wexford, Ireland, 6 pages; Describes Wexford, quarters, and the life of a soldier after the war. Notes playing sports and recreational flying. Uncertain what orders he will receive. Comments on local residents and the Sinn Fieners. "The war dropped out from under my feet in a way. All my plans have been built on it for so long that I was bewildered with the rapid change. It is hard for me to realize that it is really over and that the world is at peace." On U.S. Naval Forces Operating in European Waters. U.S. Naval Aviation Forces, Foreign Service. U.S. Naval Air Station. Wexford, Ireland stationery. See also Paul ALS to Mother, November 6, 1918; November 12, 1918.
  - 1918 December 6. Virginia Flanagan ALS to Margaret Power; [France], 4 pages; American Red Cross, Military Hospital Number 1, American Expeditionary Forces. Sends condolences to Margaret upon the death of her mother. Comments on the loss of her own mother recently after arriving in France. "While I have enjoyed my stay here I will be glad to get home to the dear Old U.S.A." "Nurses mail" cancellation, along with censor stamp.
  - 1918 December 21. Geo[rge] J. Bucher ALS to Harriet [Hudson]; Kelberg, Germany, 4 pages; Headquarters Company, 16th Field Artillery, American Expeditionary Forces. Describes the occupation troops' march into Germany, the weather, countryside. Rode four days in the Radio Detail's truck, noting how they set up a station at every stop. Grateful for the pictures and possible Christmas gift, if the mail service can accommodate all the packages being sent. Thompson Yards Inc. sent a draft for eighty-one francs to all of their "former employees who are in service overseas." Notes the tires stripped from German cars to be used for "war material." Envelope includes censor stamp.
  - 1919 January 1. Wag D. K. Irving ALS to "Sir"; Rupt-en-Woëvre, France, 3 pages; 302nd Field Artillery, Bat. C, American Expeditionary Forces. Disappointed at having not received more letters or a Christmas package from home. "... I don't mind as I am used to disappointments hoping this life will end this year for me any way & the rest of the 302." Did not get vacation, but has visited Verdun, Nancy, and Toul, France, "& quite a number of the citys that has been shook up." Had to give their traders guns and caissons to another outfit. Attending motorcycle school at Rupt, after already taking classes on trucks and tractors. Frustrated with his studies, preferring aviation, but may study flying when he returns home. "I was hauling number three Gun that sent the first shot at the Hun from the 302 I would like to be the first to step on the USA soil when we all come Marching home." Written on Knights of Columbus illustrated stationery, includes image of Knights of Columbus emblem and American Flag.